A Guide to the Lunenburg County (Va.) Deeds, 1746-1989 (bulk 1746-1935)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Lunenburg County (Va.) Deeds, 1746-1989 (bulk 1746-1935)
The Library of Virginia
1175874-1175960
39.15 cu. ft. (87 boxes)
Lunenburg County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from Lunenburg County under the accession number 42852.
Historical Information
Lunenburg County was formed in 1745 from Brunswick County. Part of Charlotte County was added in 1777.
Scope and Content
Lunenburg County (Va.) Deeds, 1746-1989 (bulk 1746-1935) consist of deeds of bargain and sale, deeds of gift, mortgages, deeds of trust, and deeds of emancipation. On presentation to the court, deeds were proved and recorded. If the deed was not witnessed, the grantor acknowledged the deed in open court. A few of the deeds include plats. Except for a few years early in the eighteenth century, slaves in Virginia were considered personal property and consequently were not usually sold by deed. However, they were often transferred in deeds of gift or were the property listed in mortgages and deeds of trust.
Deeds of bargain and sale are the most commonly recorded deed in which one individual sells property, usually land, but occasionally personal property, to another individual. Such deeds show the names of the grantor and grantee, the residence of both parties, a description of what is being sold, the consideration (or price), the location of the tract of land, the tract's boundaries, and any limitations on the property being sold. The deed was signed by the grantor, and possibly his wife or anyone else having a claim to the property, and by at least two witnesses. Appended to the deed may be a memorandum of livery of seisin, stating that the property has changed hands and that peaceful possession has taken place.
Deeds of gift are often found transferring property, either real or personal, from one individual to another "for love and affection." The degree of kinship, if any, between the grantor and grantee is sometimes stated.
Mortgages and deeds of trust were deeds where one party is indebted to another and transfers or mortgages property to a third party to secure the debt.
Prior to 1869, additional loose records were filed with deeds and were recorded in the deed books. They include the following: officials' bonds and commissions, fiduciary records, coroners' inquisitions, overseers of the poor reports, marriage contracts, school commissioners' reports, military and pension records, tax and fiscal records, bills of sale for slaves, and road and bridge records.
The coroners' inquisitions include investigations into the deaths of free negroes and slaves. Information found includes date the inquest's findings were recorded in the deed book, name of slave or free negro, name of slave owner, and cause of death. Surnames of slave owners include: Eastman, Chappell, Capells, deGraffenreid, Stokes, Pettus, Astrop, Coleman, Jones, Williams, Orgain, Shelburne, Eubank, Gee, Scott, Davis, Knight, Blackwell, Coleman, Buford, Edmundson, Cole, and Jones.
Arrangement
Organized chronologically according to date deeds were recorded in deed books.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Deed Books (1746-1869) and Indices to Deeds (1746-1900) for Lunenburg County can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm
Additional Lunenburg County Land Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Lunenburg County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans--History.; Coroners--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Free African Americans--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Overseers of the poor--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Slaveholders--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Slavery--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Slaves--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Slaves--Emancipation--Virginia--Lunenburg County.
Geographical Names:
Lunenburg County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Commissions (permissions)--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Deeds--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Free negro and slave records--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Land records--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Local government records--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Marriage records--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Mortgage deeds--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; Performance bonds--Virginia--Lunenburg County.; School records--Virginia--Lunenburg County.
Contents List
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1746-1750 (Barcode 1175874)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1751-1754 (Barcode 1175875)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1755-1758 (Barcode 1175876)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1758-1760 (Barcode 1175877)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1761-1762 (Barcode 1175878)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1762-1763 (Barcode 1175879)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1764-1765 (Barcode 1175880)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1766-1771 (Barcode 1175881)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1772-1777 (Barcode 1175882)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1778-1780 (Barcode 1175883)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1780-1785 (Barcode 1175884)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1786-1789 (Barcode 1175885)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1790-1793 (Barcode 1175886)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1794-1796 (Barcode 1175887)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1796-1798 (Barcode 1175888)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1799-1801 (Barcode 1175889)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1802-1803 (Barcode 1175890)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1804-1806 (Barcode 1175891)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1806-1808 (Barcode 1175892)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1808-1811 (Barcode 1175893)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1811-1814 (Barcode 1175894)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1814-1816 (Barcode 1175895)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1817-1819 (Barcode 1175896)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1819-1821 (Barcode 1175897)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1822-1824 (Barcode 1175898)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1824-1826 (Barcode 1175899)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1826-1828 (Barcode 1175900)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1828-1829 (Barcode 1175901)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1830-1831 (Barcode 1175902)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1832-1833 (Barcode 1175903)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1834-1835 (Barcode 1175904)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1836-1837 (Barcode 1175905)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1838-1839 (Barcode 1175906)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1840-1841 (Barcode 1175907)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1842-1843 (Barcode 1175908)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1844-1846 (Barcode 1175909)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1847-1850 (Barcode 1175910)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1851-1853 (Barcode 1175911)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1854-1856 (Barcode 1175912)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1857-1860 (Barcode 1175913)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1860-1866 (Barcode 1175914)
- Deeds (includes additional record series), 1866-1869 (Barcode 1175915)
- Deeds, 1870-1872 (Barcode 1175916)
- Deeds, 1873-1875 (Barcode 1175917)
- Deeds, 1876-1878 (Barcode 1175918)
- Deeds, 1879-1881 (Barcode 1175919)
- Deeds, 1882-1884 (Barcode 1175920)
- Deeds, 1884-1886 (Barcode 1175921)
- Deeds, 1886-1888 (Barcode 1175922)
- Deeds, 1888-1889 (Barcode 1175923)
- Deeds, 1890-1891 (Barcode 1175924)
- Deeds, 1892-1893 (Barcode 1175925)
- Deeds, 1894-1895 (Barcode 1175926)
- Deeds, 1895-1897 (Barcode 1175927)
- Deeds, 1897-1898 (Barcode 1175928)
- Deeds, 1899-1900 (Barcode 1175929)
- Deeds, 1901-1902 (Barcode 1175930)
- Deeds, 1903-1904 (Barcode 1175931)
- Deeds, 1905-1906 (Barcode 1175932)
- Deeds, 1906-1907 (Barcode 1175933)
- Deeds, 1907-1908 (Barcode 1175934)
- Deeds, 1908-1909 (Barcode 1175935)
- Deeds, 1909-1910 (Barcode 1175936)
- Deeds, 1910-1911 (Barcode 1175937)
- Deeds, 1911-1912 (Barcode 1175938)
- Deeds, 1912-1913 (Barcode 1175939)
- Deeds, 1913 (Barcode 1175940)
- Deeds, 1914 (Barcode 1175941)
- Deeds, 1914-1915 (Barcode 1175942)
- Deeds, 1915-1916 (Barcode 1175943)
- Deeds, 1916-1917 (Barcode 1175944)
- Deeds, 1917-1918 (Barcode 1175945)
- Deeds, 1918-1919 (Barcode 1175946)
- Deeds, 1919-1920 (Barcode 1175947)
- Deeds, 1920 (Barcode 1175948)
- Deeds, 1920-1921 (Barcode 1175949)
- Deeds, 1921 (Barcode 1175950)
- Deeds, 1921-1922 (Barcode 1175951)
- Deeds, 1922-1923 (Barcode 1175952)
- Deeds, 1923 (Barcode 1175953)
- Deeds, 1924 (Barcode 1175954)
- Deeds, 1924-1926 (Barcode 1175955)
- Deeds, 1927-1931 (Barcode 1175956)
- Deeds, 1933-1935, 1938 (Barcode 1175957)
- Oversize Deeds, 1752-1816 (Barcode 1175958)
- Oversize Deeds, 1752-1922 (Barcode 1175960)
- Oversize Deeds, 1817-1925 (Barcode 1175959)